<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Blog | Tad Macy]]></title>
  <link href="http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/categories/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tadmacy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-27T11:49:26-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tadmacy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tad Macy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Create an Octopress Github Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/simple-setup-of-octopress-github-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/simple-setup-of-octopress-github-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found the installation of a github blog with Octopress to be problematic. Seems like between the <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/github/">the Octopress site&rsquo;s docs</a> (which seem to be very thorough, BTW) and the <a href="https://pages.github.com/">github pages (a.k.a., blog)</a> creation docs, something was slipping between the cracks. Web searches resulted in many false leads or solutions inappropraite to my case. I got pretty frustrated. But, since it seems that others have had issues as well, I decided to knuckle down and find my own way. I put what I&rsquo;ve learned here.</p>

<p>Also, this site can be helpful: <a href="http://eduncan911.com/software/octopress-powershell-and-posh-git-oh-my.html">Eric Duncan&rsquo;s blog</a>.</p>

<p>Prerquisite: You have some experience with GitHub/git:
   * you can create a repository
   * you have git ed locally espcially the git shell
   * you have used some git commands on the command line (i.e., the Win7 GUI isn&rsquo;t useful for this thing)</p>

<p>Tools that I used:
   * Windows 7
   * Ruby 2.0.0 (There are issues with earlier versions of Ruby that have workarounds but &hellip;)
   * <a href="https://windows.github.com">GitHub for Windows 2.0</a>: the &ldquo;posh-git&rdquo; shell</p>

<ol>
<li><p>In your browser, navigate to github and create a new respository as blog. To do this you must name the new repository with your github username suffixed with &ldquo;.github.io&rdquo;, e.g., &ldquo;tadmacy.github.io&rdquo;. The blog will have the URL &ldquo;<a href="https://username.github.io">https://username.github.io</a>&rdquo; unless you wish to apply a custom domain. See the github docs for more info.</p>

<p>After clicking &ldquo;Create&rdquo;, you&rsquo;ll see a screen like this one.</p>

<p><img src="https://tadmacy.github.io/images/snaps/github-repo-create..png" title="Repo setup page" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>Make sure that the blog is empty, i.e., no README.md. Don&rsquo;t clone it or pull it to your local host.</p>

<p>We are finsihed here for now but don&rsquo;t close this page quite yet. While most of the remaining steps are performed in the git shell of your local desktop, we&rsquo;ll need to come back here to get the &ldquo;HTTP&rdquo; URL shown near the top of the page in the &ldquo;Quick setup&rdquo; block.</p>

<blockquote><p>Note that steps 2 - 4 below follow the <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/setup/">Octopress instructions</a> exactly. It is only when on the <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/github/">Deploying to GitHub</a> page that some variations may be needed.</p></blockquote></li>
<li><p>In your desktop, open the command shell and navigate to your github workspace.</p>

<pre><code>cd &lt;your-git-project-folder&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Use git to clone the Octopress framework as the basis for your blog. Your blog &ldquo;repo&rdquo; begins its life as a clone of the [<a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress">https://github.com/imathis/octopress</a>].</p>

<pre><code>git clone git://github.com/imathis/octopress.git &lt;your-blog-name&gt;
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Now we need to unpack the Octopress files:</p>

<pre><code>cd &lt;your-blog-name&gt;
bundle install
</code></pre>

<p>After some gems are checked or installed, the install process should end on success.</p></li>
<li><p>Next, we run the Octpress action script like this:</p>

<pre><code>rake install
</code></pre>

<p>This makes a few new folders. When it finishes, note that the command prompt changes. It now includes a change count indicator following &ldquo;master&rdquo;. The changes are in red because they have not been comitted yet.</p></li>
<li><p>Now, we need to add the github blogging support framework. So, run this:</p>

<pre><code>rake setup_github_pages
</code></pre>

<p>This command will ask you for the URL of the remote repository. Get the correct URL from the github page in of step 1. Your HTTP URL shown at the top of the page in the &ldquo;Quick setup&rdquo; block.</p>

<p>Among many changes, note that a &ldquo;source&rdquo; branch has been created. Your shell prompt has changed, too. Now &ldquo;master&rdquo; is &ldquo;source&rdquo;. And there are more uncommited materials.</p>

<blockquote><p>More detailed information on this setup process can be found on <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/github/">the Octopress site</a>.</p></blockquote></li>
<li><p>At this point the <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/github/">Octopress documentation</a> seems to miss a step. Or, more accurately, the rake scripts miss an important step: setting the git origin for the &ldquo;_deploy&rdquo; folder just created. To fix that, do this:</p>

<pre><code>[source +2 ~3 -0 !]&gt; cd .\_deploy
[master]&gt; git remote set-url origin https://github.com/tadmacy/tadmacy.github.io.git
</code></pre>

<p>You can use the git remote command to verify that origin is properly set:</p>

<pre><code>[master]&gt; git remote -v
</code></pre>

<p>Don&rsquo;t forget to do a &ldquo;cd ..&rdquo; to get back the the &ldquo;source&rdquo; branch.</p>

<p>In your &ldquo;source&rdquo; branch, you want to verify that the origin URL is correctly set. Do that using the process above while in the &ldquo;source&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Some people report that the origin is not set for source either, but it was okay in my install.</p></li>
<li><p>You should now be able to commit changes to github (be sure you are in &ldquo;source&rdquo;) with the two following commands:</p>

<pre><code>[source +2 ~3 -0 !]&gt; rake generate
[source +2 ~3 -0 !]&gt; rake deploy
</code></pre>

<p>Watch for errors. Hope you had none and are ready to move on!</p>

<p>By the way, there is a sortcut command that does these two things.</p>

<pre><code>[source +2 ~3 -0 !] rake gen_deploy
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>You may have noticed that we did not commit the changes. Let&rsquo;s do that now. In &ldquo;source&rdquo;:</p>

<pre><code>[source +2 ~2 -0 !]&gt; git add .
[source +117 ~2 -0]&gt; git commit -m "first commit" 
[source +117 ~2 -0]&gt; rake gen_deploy
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Now you may want to go back to github in your browser and look at the blog repository file list. You should see a lot files there now. And after a few minutes, your blog should be visible at &ldquo;your-blog-name.github.io&rdquo;.</p></li>
<li><p>Lastly resume the instructions at Octopress. Be sure to apply the instructions in &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t forget to commit the source for your blog.&rdquo;</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Other next steps you&rsquo;ll find there:</p>

<ul>
<li>Personalize your blog by editing the &ldquo;_config.yml&rdquo; file.</li>
<li>Add posts to the &ldquo;source_posts&rdquo; folder, commit them, and run rake gen_deploy to push them to your new blog.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Edit Octpress GitHub Layout and CSS]]></title>
    <link href="http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/how-to-modify-octopress-githhub-layout-and-css/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/how-to-modify-octopress-githhub-layout-and-css</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my github blog which was generated from a clone of the Octopress blog, I did this to change some CSS.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>In the &ldquo;source/stylesheets&rdquo; folder in the root of the repository, I added the file &ldquo;overrides.css&rdquo;.</p></li>
<li><p>To modify the HTML header to include the new CSS file, I edited the &ldquo;source/head.html&rdquo; to include the new link.</p></li>
<li><p>Do a &ldquo;commit -a -m &lsquo;my new css&rsquo;&rdquo; followed by &ldquo;rake gen_deploy&rdquo;</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Commit Octopress Posts]]></title>
    <link href="http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/09/08/how-to-commit-octopress-posts/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/09/08/how-to-commit-octopress-posts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After creating a new post, three commands are run to update the blog on github.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Navigate to the source folder of your repository. In my Windows 7 host it is &ldquo;Documents\GitHub\tadmacy.github.io [source]&rdquo;. I use the posh-git shell.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve added or renamed files:</p>

<pre><code class="tcsh">[source]&gt; git add .
[source]&gt; git commit -a -m "add post"
</code></pre>

<p>-or-</p>

<p>If you only edited existing files:</p>

<pre><code>[source]&gt; git commit -a -m "add posts"
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Deploy changes to github (because &ldquo;rake deploy&rdquo; does not seem to do the job):</p>

<pre><code class="tcsh">[source]&gt; rake gen_deploy
</code></pre></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Create an Octopress Github Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/09/02/managing-multiple-versions-of-ruby-in-windows/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/09/02/managing-multiple-versions-of-ruby-in-windows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trying to keep up with new software releases can be tough. I&rsquo;ve had the case where I need multiple versions of Ruby installed to satisfy the requirements of some tools or gems. I found <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/3648744/how-to-have-multiple-versions-of-ruby-and-rails-and-their-combinations-on-windo">this article at StackOverflow</a> that helped me. Locate the post by Harish Shetty and everything you need is there. In summary, the best option for me was the installation of the &ldquo;pik&rdquo; gem.</p>

<p>Despite the claim by some that this project is out of date, I have yet to find a better option. And, the assertion by some that it not needed is false. I need it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extending a Cordova/Phonegap Contact List Tutorial]]></title>
    <link href="http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/08/31/extending-a-cordova-phonegap-contact-list-tutorial/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tadmacy.github.io/blog/2014/08/31/extending-a-cordova-phonegap-contact-list-tutorial</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>The completion of the tutorial intended to accompany this post has been delayed. Please check back soon or drop me a note if you have questions or a particular interest in this work.</blockquote>


<p>I was anxious to learn some new frameworks, build a mobile app using a cross platform tool or SDK, and apply this effort to produce something useful. As it happened our department needed a better way to distribute our internal emergency contact information. This seemed to be a great fit for a side project &ndash; a mobile app that worked like the native contact list in the iPhone.</p>

<p>But a few requirements quickly emerged. Most of our staff carry iPhones, but a few have Android devices. It would be a big win if the app ran on both the iOS and Android platforms. At first this seemed like a show stopper considering the limited time available for a side project. Yes, I&rsquo;ve done a bit of iOS work; a bit of Java &ndash; but no Android development at all.</p>

<p>A while back I had read about several cross device SDK&rsquo;s and experimented with Intel&rsquo;s XDK. Most of the cross device SDKs use tools familiar to front-end developers: HTML5, CSS and JavaScript/jQuery. It would be a real advantage to leverage my skills in that area. I liked XDK when I tried it. It looks like its been improved, too.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d also heard some good things about PhoneGap. A few Google searches, a little reading and I hit upon  Cordova (aka PhoneGap) 3.x Tutorial by Christophe Coenraets. Perfect! Using some new tools like Nodejs/npm, Handlebars framework and TopCoat CSS? Great. I decided to get going and try PhoneGap. The tutorial was great. Got the app up in running quite quickly.</p>

<p>But, hold on a second.</p>

<p>My app was to contain personal data - real data. I&rsquo;d have to authenticate to our central LDAP/AD authentication services. Also, this contact list would require data not stored in the mainstream institutional user repositories so a well supported secure database would be needed, too. This little side project was quickly blossoming into something much bigger. But being the Drupal guy here, too, I&rsquo;d built an institutional news service in Drupal with authentication to AD. It occurred to me that I could build a small module for this application to extend the Drupal user data to include some additional fields. And, since Drupal has optional RESTful services, my backend issues were starting to fall into place.</p>

<p>Luckily, I underestimated the time needed to pull all of this off and charged ahead.</p>

<p>So, my tutorial, Extending the Cordova/Phonegap Contact List, builds upon the terrific Cordova (aka PhoneGap) 3.x Tutorial by Christophe Coenraets.
Note that Christophe updated his tutorial in early July of 2014 and it has some significant changes here. My tutorial is based on the pre-July version.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
